Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, so today's דף Daf is
כ"ג. Chaf Gimmel. We pick up towards the bottom of כ"ג, Chaf
Gimmel, or the middle,
and it's כלים הנגמרים בטהרה Kelim Hanigmarim Betahara about almost exactly in
the middle by the two dots, the beginning of the line כלים
הנגמרים בטהרה. Kelim Hanigmarim Betahara. So we spent a good amount of
time dealing with the issue about כלי בתוך כלי Kli Betoch Kli
about immersing one vessel in another vessel, and that and then the
second one about carrying a מדרס Midras some type of a seat
to the point that the גמרא Gemara even thought maybe it meant
even if it was a טהור Tahor מדרס, Midras, but certainly a
טמא Tamei one and carrying קודש Kodesh at the same time. And
now we turn on to number number three. So it is כלים
הנגמרים בטהרה. Kelim Hanigmarim Betahara. Vessels even if they are completed in
a state of purity, you still would have to immerse them before
you would use them for קודש Kodesh purposes but not for תרומה
Truma purposes. So the גמרא Gemara says: דגמינהו מאן? Degaminhu man? Who
was the one that completed them, who was the artisan? Who was
supervising the process and telling us that it was completed
בטהרה? Betahara? So אילימא דגמינהו חבר, Ileima degaminhu chaver, if it was
a חבר chaver somebody who could be trusted about these matters, so
למה להו טבילה? lamah lehu tvila? So what could be any possible
reason of requiring טבילה? tvila? He's supervising the whole process. אלא דגמינהו
עם הארץ, Ela degaminhu am ha'aretz, so it was an עם הארץ
am ha'aretz who supervised. So נגמרים בטהרה קרי להו? nigmarim betahara kari
lehu? So how could you even describe the scenario as that they
were finished in a state of purity? Either make up your mind,
either that we obviously are assuming it's impure and then anyway you
would need to go put it in the מקוה Mikvah even for
תרומה Truma purposes, or if it really was supervised, why should we
need to dunk it in the מקוה Mikvah and never even had
a chance to become טמא? Tamei? So the גמרא Gemara said: אמר
רבה בר שילא אמר רב מתנא אמר שמואל, Amar Rabba bar Shila
amar Rav Matna amar Shmuel, לעולם דגמינהו חבר. le'olam degaminhu chaver. Okay,
it was a חבר chaver who was supervising. And he was actually
doing it, doing it and supervising. ומשום צינורא דעם הארץ. Umishum tzinora
de'am ha'aretz. And we're afraid of again this thing similar to the
whole issue about the טומאה tuma of vessels that we dealt with
yesterday. Oh because the other one that I also had covered was
liquid that's מטמא metamei a vessel and it's מטמא metamei parts without
being מטמא metamei other parts and that's because חז"ל Chazal made all
normally liquid would be at most a ראשון rishon and wouldn't have
the ability to מטמא metamei a vessel but they were concerned about
this case of liquids that are actually an אב, av, which are
the fluids that come from a זב, zav, זבה, zava, and a
נדה. niddah. Now that's an אב הטומאה. av hatuma. That by the
way is called in the rabbinic language צינורא, tzinora, צינורא דזב. tzinora
dezav. And a צינורא tzinora is actually like a type of a
faucet. I always find it quite funny that it calls these things
so the fluids of a זב zav are like the faucets, the
things that come out of the body. So those types of a
thing is
an אב הטומאה. av hatuma. So we're concerned that somehow although it
was being supervised and in a minute the גמרא Gemara is going
to say it was being supervised how did this happen? But we're
assuming somehow some spit from a זב zav or זבה zava or
נדה niddah got on the vessel. So let's take a look.
Okay but when did this happen? דנפל אימת? Dinafal eimas? When would
be concerned that this happened that it hit the vessel? אילימא מקמי
דגמרי, Ileima mikmi degamrei, if it was before the vessel finished being
completed, so לאו מנא הוא, lav manah hu, it's not a vessel
and it can't become טמא. tamei. אלא בתר דגמרי, Ela batar degamrei,
after it was completed, מיזהר זהיר ביה הוא. mizhar zahir beh hu.
So that's when the serious supervision starts.
The חבר chaver who is supervising and making the vessel, in a
way he doesn't really care what happened to it prior to it
being completed because it's not yet fit for becoming טמא. tamei. But
once he puts it in the kiln and it's about to be
completed and it's finally then completed and then it's a vessel that
could become טמא tamei then he starts supervising. So the גמרא Gemara
says: When did this possible טמא tamei spit go down on the
vessel? If it's before it was finished, it's not a problem. If
it was
at while after it's finished, that's when the חבר chaver is supervising
it. So how could this have happened? So the גמרא Gemara says:
לעולם מקמי דגמרי. Le'olam mikmi degamrei. So here's the scenario. It hit
the vessel before it had been completed. And therefore the degree of
it wasn't being highly supervised yet.
ודילמא בעידנא דגמרי עדיין לחה היא. Vedi'lma be'idna degamrei adayin lecha ha'ei.
So maybe though even though it wasn't yet being highly supervised because
it wasn't yet completed and some spit hit it, and then when
it was completed that little bit of that spit was still on
it and then it made it טמא. tamei. Of course it's turned
in the kiln and it was... yeah, so I don't know, maybe
it was something that was air dried or whatever, although if that
were true then it wouldn't... let's not make it a pottery vessel,
let's make it I don't know like a wood vessel or a
metal vessel. Okay so therefore that spit is still on it and
then when it was completed and that's when the supervision begins but
there was still old spit on it and that's what made it
טמא. tamei. Of course one would say that if that's a scenario
that could happen and a חבר chaver supervises he just... starts supervising
early. Anyway, and what's an עם הארץ am ha'aretz doing around in
your shop, you know, if you're trying to make it טהור? tahor?
But by the way, remember, you know, we saw there were a
lot of interactions with עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz, you know, it was
that whole thing of that balance of interacting but, but, you know,
protecting טומאה tum'ah and טהרה taharah and so on. So sure, of
course you need workers in your shop and you're going to hire,
you know, not just חברים, chaverim, you'll hire עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz,
but you'll want to supervise when it gets to the stage of
it's almost being complete, you know, that's when your supervision will be
needed, but there might still be something on it.
That was Rashi's scenario where the חבר chaver is holding the vessel
and the עם הארץ am ha'aretz is standing right there.
Right, exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, so
and that's why you need it, but of course that's only a
חשש רחוק, chashash rachok, that's a very distant concern, so it's only
something we apply by קודש Kodesh and we don't apply by תרומה.
Terumah. Now by the way, getting to this issue of the degree
of interaction of חבר chaver and עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, תוספות Tosafot
is bothered exactly by this scenario. How could you have an עם
הארץ am ha'aretz around your shop when you're trying to create כלים
בטהרה? keilim betaharah? And תוספות Tosafot actually suggests maybe it doesn't literally
mean an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. Maybe it means a חבר, chaver,
but a חבר chaver who only is careful one level less than
you, like only is careful for תרומה Terumah purposes, not for קודש
Kodesh purposes. And remember how we talked before like his clothes have
to be considered a מדרס, midras, anybody one lower level than you
is like completely טמא tamei vis-a-vis you. So for that so if
that type of person was around your shop, it'd be a fellow
חבר, chaver, but he's a little bit on the lower level, his
spit is also has to be considered totally טמא tamei and create
this problem and so on. So תוספות Tosafot create so, a, it's
helpful to remind ourselves it's not just like an attitude towards עמי
הארץ, amei ha'aretz, although obviously it was much more severe towards עמי
הארץ, amei ha'aretz, but it's an attitude to anybody lower than you
on the level. But also תוספות Tosafot trying to, you know, get
his head around this idea that you can try to create טהר
כלים tahar keilim and have עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz around in your
shop. But I actually think that that's, you know, that's a that's
the case. Like we saw, you could have עמי הארץ, amei ha'aretz,
you know, be transporting your טהור tahor wine and oil, you know,
these were people, like, you know, they might have even been higher
than you in other regards, meaning religiously maybe there was one stratification,
but who knows socially, right? It could have been, you know, that
the, it could have been that Bill Gates was an עם הארץ,
am ha'aretz, you know, could be that the wealthy people, you know,
they're not the ones that are being careful on טומאה tum'ah and
טהרה. taharah. It doesn't mean that the חברים chaverim were always in
a higher socioeconomic status than the חברים, chaverim, than the עמי הארץ.
amei ha'aretz. So we shouldn't think of the עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz
as like, oh, the lowly people of society, you know. This was
within the ranking of, you know, of the care of טומאה tum'ah
and טהרה, taharah, sort of like within the rabbinic stratification. So of
course you're having interactions with these people in other realms and therefore
they could be around in your shop. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this, ודילמא, u'dilma, okay,
okay,
so the גמרא Gemara now goes on to another point. טבילה אין
הערב שמש לא. tevilah in ha'erev shemesh lo.
Now, we only require that you immerse this vessel, because again, it's
only this distant concern, we're only going to be concerned about it
for קודש, Kodesh, but, you know, and even if it were טמא,
tamei, it's also built on a rabbinic issue of the spit of
an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, that we're going to treat as if
it was the spit of a זב. zav. So it's a very
distant concern, we only apply it by קודש. Kodesh. And what do
we tell you? Do we tell you to immerse it? Now, if
it was really טמא, tamei, you'd have to immerse something and wait
for it to be nightfall for it to be totally טהור. tahor.
Okay, but here it doesn't mention waiting for nightfall, it just says
immerse. So the גמרא Gemara is inferring that given that this is
only a מעלה, ma'alah, and it's only by קודש, Kodesh, and it's
a very, you know, sort of like, you know, small concern, the
language says you immerse, you immerse, but you don't have to wait
for nightfall. And that makes a lot of sense. But now the
גמרא Gemara is going to check if that's right, you know, check
if that's correct. Okay, so טבילה אין, tevilah in, you only have
to immerse it, הערב שמש לא, ha'erev shemesh lo, and but not
you don't have to wait for night. מתניתין דלא כרבי אליעזר. matnitin
d'lo k'Rabbi Eliezer. It's not like Rabbi Eliezer, no. שפופרת שחתכה לחטאת.
shepoperes shehatachah lechatat.
You have a type of a straw, like or type of, you
know, think of like a piece of bamboo or whatever, you're cutting
it so that you're going to use it for a like container
for the water of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, okay, so maybe
you're distributing it like we discussed the other day to like local
places, and you're going to have contained the water of the ashes
of the פרה אדומה parah adumah into this like little, you know,
bamboo container, and you're and so you're you're cutting this this piece,
and that's what you did, and essentially you made it a vessel,
right? You took this piece of bamboo, you cut it down to
size, you made it into this nice almost like, you know, eyelash
applicator type of a thing. So, you know, פרה אדומה parah adumah
applicator, you made it into a vessel. Okay, לחטאת. lechatat. רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, יטבול מיד, yitbol miyad, you have to dunk
it in the מקווה, mikvah, right? Because that's a vessel that was
complete, what did we learn in our משנה? mishnah? You gotta dunk
it in the מקווה. mikvah. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, יטמא
ואחר כך יטבול. yitma v'achar kach yitbol. First you get it טמא
tamei before putting it in the מקווה. mikvah. Now why would you
proactively get something you're about to use for פרה אדומה parah adumah
טמא? tamei?
Sort of like a bully.
Well, yeah, exactly. So this is based on the principle that there
was a whole debate with with the צדוקים Tzadokim around aspects of
the פרה אדומה parah adumah and particularly the question about whether the
עבודה avodah of the פרה אדומה parah adumah could be done with
a כהן kohen that had gone to the מקווה mikvah but it
wasn't yet like nightfall. So the גמרא Gemara actually says that they
would actually go out of their way to prove the צדוקים Tzedukim
wrong to get the כהן Kohen and here we're seeing other parts
of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah טמא tamei and put them in
the מקווה Mikveh and then do it before with you know before
nightfall you know so they'd have this crazy leniency because normally you'd
expect them to be super crazy מחמיר machmir just to show that
the צדוקים Tzedukim were wrong. Of course then it says since we
were lenient in that one area we were super crazy מחמיר machmir
in everything else about the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. Okay fine. So
anyway that's what's going on here. We want to make this tube
something that was טמא tamei and has gone to the מקווה Mikveh
and hasn't yet been nightfall. So that's what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
is saying here. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is saying don't just סתם
stam dunk it. You gotta get it because you gotta get it
really טמא tamei and then put it in the מקווה. Mikveh. Okay,
so יטבח אחר יטבח yitvach achir yitvach ואווינא בה vaavina bah דחתכא
מאן. dechat chamman.
Now who is cutting this, who is making this into a vessel?
אילימא דחתכא חבר, Ileima dechatcha chaver, if a חבר chaver cutting it,
למה לי טבילה? lamah li tvilah?
So again this is sort of like the same case although it's
sort of not yet bringing in the תקנה takanah of our משנה,
Mishnah, the מעלה maalah of our משנה. Mishnah. So without yet bringing
in our משנה Mishnah that this general principle of immersing vessels, it
says if a חבר chaver supervised why should you have to immerse
it at all? ואלא דחתכא עם הארץ, Ve'ela dechatcha am haaretz, תו
נם tu nam עם הארץ am haaretz supervised. ובהא לימא Veha leima
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua יטמא? yitma? So why would רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua say you have to get proactively get it טמא? tamei? If
an עם הארץ am haaretz is doing it we completely consider it
טמא tamei already anyway. ויטבול, Veyitbol, הטמא לקאי, hatamei leka'ei,
it's already considered טמא tamei if an עם הארץ am haaretz is
supervising it. והאמר רבה בר שילא אמר רב מתנא אמר שמואל לעולם
דחתכא חבר. Vehamar Rabbah bar Shila amar Rav Matna amar Shmuel leolam
dechatcha chaver. Again, okay, a חבר chaver did it. ומשום צינור דעם
הארץ, Umishum tzinor deam haaretz, okay and again the reason that we
have this concern that we have to put it in the מקווה
Mikveh even though a חבר chaver did it is there might be
some spit from an עם הארץ. am haaretz. דנפל אימת, Denafal eimei,
now when did that spit hit the hit this vessel? אילימא מקמי
דחתכא, Ileima mikmei dechatcha, if it was before you cut it, הלאו
מנא הוא, halav man hu, it shouldn't be a problem, it wasn't
a vessel. ואלא בתר דחתכא, Ve'ela batar dechatcha, after it was cut,
מיזר זהיר בה, mizar zahir bah, at that stage you're being you're
supervising it, you're being careful. ולעולם מקמי דחתכא, Uleolam mikmei dechatcha, fine,
it fell before it was cut. ודילמא בעידנא דחתכא, Vedilma beidna dechatcha,
but maybe when it came time to cut it, עדיין ליחא היא,
adayin leichah hi,
it was still moist, that liquid was still on it, it was
still moist and it made it טמא. tamei. Exactly what we said
before. So basically you cut this thing, we have the idea of
our משנה Mishnah that you have to dunk it in the מקווה
Mikveh for קודש Kodesh and for פרה אדומה Parah Adumah purposes and
that's why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying dunk it in the
מקווה. Mikveh. Now why is רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua saying go out
of your way and make it really טמא, tamei, not just this
vague concern? So let's take a look. בשלמא לרבי יהושע, Bishlama leRabbi
Yehoshua, היינו דקא מיקל לצדוקים. hainu dekaheikel leTzedukim.
According to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that you make it really טמא,
tamei, that's how we're going to use this as a way of
saying that we're not doing what the צדוקים Tzedukim say. דתנן, Detnan,
מטמאים היו metamin hayu את הכהן השורף את הפרה, et hakohen hasoref
et haparah,
they would get the כהן Kohen who was going to do the
עבודה avodah to burn the פרה, Parah, they would get him טמא
tamei and get him immersed in the מקווה Mikveh but not wait
till nightfall so he would still be a little טמא tamei להוציא
מליבן של צדוקים, lehotzi miliban shel Tzedukim, in order to like, you
know, undermine the position of the צדוקים. Tzedukim. שהיו אומרים Shehayu omerim
במעורב שמש הייתה נעשית. bemeiorev shemesh hayetah naasah.
You could only do the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah by somebody who
had already been nightfall, who already had been completely טהור. tahor. They
did it with somebody who went to the מקווה Mikveh before it
was completely טהור tahor and that's what you're going to do with
this tube. That explains רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. Now what the גמרא's
Gemara saying is like this: okay, we have this case, before getting
it טמא, tamei, this tube required immersion because of the מעלה maalah
in our משנה. Mishnah. But we are saying that it sounds like
our משנה Mishnah you would only have to immerse it, you wouldn't
have to wait for nightfall, right? In any case, forget פרה אדומה.
Parah Adumah. The most you would have to do when a vessel
was finished בטהרה betaharah was immerse it and then you could start
using it immediately. So if that's true, we understand why רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua says that's not going to be good enough for פרה
אדומה. Parah Adumah. I mean yes, it'll be טהור tahor for פרה
אדומה, Parah Adumah, but it won't be good enough to prove our
point for the צדוקים. Tzedukim. Because it's not like we're doing any
leniency then. That's just the normal הלכה. halakhah. You finish a vessel
בטהרה, betaharah, you dunk it in the מקווה, Mikveh, you use it
immediately. If we want to show that we're being lenient and going
against the צדוקים, Tzedukim, we have to get it really טמא, tamei,
put it in the מקווה Mikveh and use it before nightfall when
it's not yet fully טהור. tahor. So that makes sense. That's why
רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua saying it's not enough to just rely on
this normal תקנה, takanah, that doesn't prove anything in this case. That
makes sense. אלא לרבי אליעזר, Ela leRabbi Eliezer, but according to רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, what are you doing that is undermining the position
of the צדוקים? Tzedukim? You're just doing the normal immersing and using
which is what you always do when something is finished בטהרה. betaharah.
So wait a minute, אי אמרת, iy amart, maybe, but the גמרא's
Gemara assuming that they're both working with the same parameters. אלא אי
אמרת בשלמא בעלמא בעינא הערב שמש, Ela iy amart bishlama be'alma beinan
ha'erev shemesh, if you say that this מעלה maalah requires immersing new
vessels and waiting for nightfall, היינו דקא מיקל לצדוקים, hainu dekaheikel leTzedukim,
then you'll be actually undermining the צדוקים, Tzedukim, you'll be using this
before nightfall. אלא אי אמרת בעלמא לא בעינא הערב שמש, Ela iy
amart be'alma lo beinan ha'erev shemesh, but if normally this whole מעלה
maalah never demands waiting for nightfall, so מאי היכר לצדוקים איכא? mai
heiker leTzedukim ika? So what are you doing that shows a greater
leniency by the פרה Parah that's undermining the צדוקים? Tzedukim? So אמר
רב, amar Rav, so said רב, Rav, by the way, you know,
it's so interesting, it shows you like all of the different people
that you had a way. worry about in the time of the
rabbis. We're going to have to be super careful about the עמי
הארץ *amei ha'aretz* and about different levels of טומאה Tumah *tumah* and
טהרה *taharah* and how all of these are various מעלות ma'alot, *ma'alot*.
Then we're going to have to deal with our dealings with the
צדוקים Tzedukim. *Tzaddukim* and figure out what things we're doing in order
to reject the צדוקים Tzedukim. *Tzaddukim*. Then of course you have to
worry about the כותים *Kutim*. Then and then nothing before you get
to non-Jews. So anyway, so it's quite fascinating all these different players
in the rabbinic sort of world there. Exactly, not so different today.
Anyway, so what's the answer? So what did you do here that
was lenient if normally anyway you start using it immediately? אלא *Ella*,
so אמר רבא *amar Rava*, so says רבא *Rava*, דף סג עמוד
ב *daf samech gimel amud bet*, עשאוה כטמאי שרץ sheretz *asauha k'tamei
sheretz*. Really what they did was, okay, it's a little like you'd
say it's almost a little circular, but what they did was they
said a normal vessel that's finished בטהרה *b'taharah*, you know, we don't
really make it טמא Tamei, *tamei*. At most maybe we'll consider it
I don't know maybe like a שני sheni *sheni* or something like
that and and we say dunk it in the מקוה Mikvah. *mikvah*,
right? But when it's being done for the sake of,
wait a minute, let me just check רש״י Rashi *Rashi*.
Yes, when it's being done for the sake of a חטאת *chatas*,
you make it as if it was a ראשון Rishon, *rishon*, as
if the vessel had touched a שרץ Sheretz. *sheretz*. And therefore since
now you give it a higher degree of טומאה tumah *tumah* and
you're still going to use it before waiting for nightfall, that'll prove
to the צדוקים Tzedukim *Tzaddukim* that you're being lenient. Of course the
question is, how do the צדוקים tzedukim? *Tzaddukim* know that you're treating
it more weightily? So the question would be, well, what would happen
if this tube would actually have I don't know touched some food?
So if it was a normal vessel that you were making for
קודש kodesh *kodesh* purposes and it touched food, okay, no problem. You
need a ראשון rishon. *rishon* to be מטמא metamei *m'tamei* food. But
if it's a vessel you're making for חטאת *chatas* purposes, for פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah. *parah adumah* purposes and it touched food, it would
make it טמא Tamei, *tamei*. So his basic answer is we normally
treat those vessels more טמא Tamei. *tamei* and therefore by allowing you
to use it without waiting for nightfall, it is a special lenient
thing. Okay, you're right, a normal vessel using it right after immersion
is not a leniency, but vessels for a חטאת *chatas*, for פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah, *parah adumah* we treat more weightily and therefore it
is lenient to allow you to use it right away. So let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אלא מעתה *Ella
me'atah*, if that's what you're saying, how we treat these vessels made
for פרה אדומה parah adumah *parah adumah* before they're immersed as if
they're a ראשון rishon. *rishon*, לא תטמא אדם *lo titamei adam*, then
the vessel should not be able to make a person טמא Tamei
*tamei* because remember a person can only become a ראשון rishon *rishon*,
he can only be טמא tamei *tamei* through an אב Av *av*.
So, so the vessel according to you should not be able to
make a person טמא tamei *tamei*. אלמה תניא Tanya, *Almah tanya*, why
do we teach in a ברייתא braita, *braisa*, חותכה *chotchah*, the one
who cuts the tube, מטבילה *matbilah*, and the one who's immersing the
tube, טעון טבילה Tevilah. *te'un tveilah*, have to go to the מקוה
Mikvah. *mikvah* because they've handled this before it became טהור Tahor *tahor*?
So that actually is a very nice evidence of how we're treating
this more weightily, that even anybody who handles it before they've immersed
it becomes טמא tamei. *tamei*. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, but
that means it has to be treated as an אב Av *av*.
The only thing that can make a person a טמא tamei *tamei*
is if it's an אב av *av*. Okay, so גמרא gemara *Gemara*
says, ואלא *v'ella* fine, עשאוה כטמאי מת Meis, *asauha k'tamei meis*. They
made this tube as if it had touched a dead body. And
therefore it's an אב av, *av*. And that's why number one anybody
who handles it before it's immersed becomes טמא tamei *tamei* and that's
why number two it's an obvious leniency to use it before waiting
for nightfall.
Why lenient like an אב Av? *av*?
So, well because again we're just super מחמיר Machmir, *machmir* by things
relating to פרה אדומה parah adumah, *parah adumah*. So the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* says אי הכי *ee hachi*, one minute, you can't say you
made it like it touched a dead body. ותיבעי הזאה שלישי shelishi
ושביעי *v'tibaye haza'ah shlishi v'shvi'i*. You shouldn't be able to use it
until you sprinkle the ashes of another פרה אדומה parah adumah, *parah
adumah* on it. So אלמה תניא *almah tanya*, why do we teach
in a ברייתא braita. *braisa*, חותכה ומטבילה טעון טבילה *chotchah u'matbilah te'un
tveilah*, as that's one who cuts it and the one who immerses
it has to go to the מקוה Mikvah, *mikvah*, and טבילה אין
הזאה שלישי Shelishi, ושביעי לא *tveilah in haza'ah shlishi v'shvi'i lo*, they
have to go to the מקוה Mikvah, *mikvah* but they don't have
to be sprinkled on it הזאה שלישי Shelishi, ושביעי *haza'ah shlishi v'shvi'i*?
Now that's actually a little bit funny because if they made the
thing as an אב Av. *av*, the person's only a ראשון rishon
*rishon*, the person wouldn't actually have to go to the מקוה Mikvah
*mikvah*, I mean wouldn't have to do the sprinkling of the ashes
of the פרה אדומה Para Aduma *parah adumah*, right?
If the vessel had actually touched a dead body, the vessel is
a טמא מת Tamei Meis *tmei meis*, it's an אב הטומאה Av
Hatumah *av hatumah*, that needs to have the whole ashes sprinkled on
it to be טהור Tahor *tahor*. Okay, but then somebody touches that
vessel, they're a ראשון rishon. *rishon*, they don't need to be, you
know, that's only a one-day טומאה tumah *tumah*, they don't need to
have the ashes sprinkled on them. So I don't know if your
if your anybody notes that or whatever, but it's a little bit
imprecise here. It really means that the vessel would need sprinkling שלישי
Shelishi. ושביעי *shlishi v'shvi'i*, not the person. Does your English or your
notes say anything about that?
No.
That's the way it's Steinsaltz. What you described is what the...
Right, so why
is
it imprecise in the...?
Because it says
חותכה ומטבילה טעון טבילה *chotchah
u'matbilah te'un tveilah*, so the טבילה *tveilah* is going on the one
who cuts it.
Yeah, oh because it says...
It should say טעונה, Te'unah. it should say טעונה. Yeah, right.
If the question is, anyway, but the point is it's clear that
all you're doing is immersing the vessel. And if you treat the
vessel as if it touched a מת, Met, so that explains why
the person is טמא, tamei, but it doesn't explain why it's sufficient
to just immerse the vessel. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא עשוה
כטמאי מת בשביעי שלו. Ella asu'ah kitemei meis bishvi'i shelo. They made
the vessel like it had touched a dead body and it had
gone through the process of day three and day seven of the
sprinkling the ashes and it was day seven of having touched a
dead body and all that was left was for having it dunked
in a מקוה. Mikvah, So basically
what they did was they turned this vessel into an אב הטומאה
Av Hatumah that could be טהור Tahor? by going to the מקוה.
Mikvah When do you have an אב הטומאה Av Hatumah that could
be טהור Tahor? just by going to the מקוה, Mikvah meaning a
normal אב הטומאה Av Hatumah is a dead body, somebody who touched
a dead body, okay, a dead carcass of an animal, you can't
put that in a מקוה, Mikvah. or somebody who basically is like
a זב Zav and a זבה Zavah and a נדה? Niddah? And
they can only, they have to be a person, they're not a
vessel, and they can only go to the מקוה Mikvah, right at
the, like, you know, like after seven days. So which category does
this become, that it's an אב הטומאה Av Hatumah that can go
into the מקוה, Mikvah right, like, you know, on the last day?
I mean, can go into the מקוה Mikvah, and be טהור? Tahor
What אב הטומאה Av Hatumah can just go into the מקוה Mikvah
and be טהור? Tahor, Well, if it had been something that had
touched a dead body and had gone through the process of the
sprinkling of day three and day seven and now then it could
be an אב הטומאה Av Hatumah that all it needs now is
to go to the מקוה. Mikvah, So it's putting it in this
very, very bizarre category in order to allow it to be טהור
Tahor by going into the מקוה, Mikvah but in order to allow
it to give it serious weight, in order to make it, you
know, in order to give this real חומרה Chumra by פרה אדומה.
para aduma. By the way, it's interesting that it didn't consider another
category, which is I think what the גמרא Gemara is going to
get to, there is one other אב הטומאה Av Hatumah that you
could dunk that is a vessel and not a person that you
could dunk and make it טהור, Tahor. which is the מושב, Moshav,
the מדרס Midras of a זב Zav and a זבה Zavah and
a נדה. Niddah. That would have to wait seven days as well,
but anyway, but it could be, you could say it's the seventh
day of a מדרס Midras of a זב Zav and a זבה.
Zavah. But those have to be things that are fit for sitting
on. So the only type of a thing that could be a
vessel that's not fit for sitting on, that has, that's an אב
הטומאה Av Hatumah, that could be טהור Tahor. by going to the
מקוה Mikvah. is something that had touched a dead body and had
the ashes sprinkled on day three and day seven and is now
just awaiting טבילה. So basically what it's saying is, we have made
this vessel, if it's prepared for פרה אדומה, para aduma, we're going
to be super מחמיר, Machmir. treat it like an אב הטומאה, Av
Hatumah say any person who handles it, any
person who handles an אב Av is a ראשון, rishon. and that's
where we're making super מחמיר. And on the other hand, we're going
to be מקיל Meikil and say once you dunked it in the
מקוה, Mikvah, you can use it right away and you don't have
to wait for nightfall. And that's how we are undermining the צדוקים.
tzedukim And that's a particular leniency. By normal vessels of course you
dunk them and you use them immediately, but this is a vessel
we're treating as an אב הטומאה Av Hatumah, and that's why it's
a real leniency to undermine the צדוקים. Tzadokim Yes. Right.
So what you're doing is you're taking something that had like, that's
affected predominantly by the variable of time and you're saying that time,
like its status is affected by that and saying that that's not...
Right.
Well, time and actually actions, the sprinkling and so on, right.
It doesn't have to be seven days.
Right, it's all a fiction because it didn't actually touch a dead
body. What it's really just saying is, is that
if I didn't need to give you a biblical, like, you know,
a biblical parallel, I would just say, you know what the rabbis
did? They said we're going to make it an אב הטומאה, Av
Hatumah, but then they're going to also say you can dunk it
in the מקוה Mikvah. and it'll be טהור. Tahor. And fine, you'd
be happy. Okay, it's an אב הטומאה, Av Hatumah you dunk it
in the מקוה, Mikvah. it's טהור. Tahor But then you might say,
oh that's crazy, you never have an אב הטומאה Av Hatumah, that
you dunk in a מקוה mikvah and it's טהור. Tahor. Well you
do, you have a vessel that touched טמא tamei. מת Met and
it's on day seven etc., etc., etc. So you know, so the
point is it's not completely absurd the scenario, but the basic point
is it didn't really touch a dead body, they're trying to give
it this great stringency of treating it as an אב Av and
at the same time give you a way of solving it and
bringing it to the מקוה. mikvah? And how do you have that
hybrid? There are, there is a time when you can find that
actual hybrid of those two.
So publicly you see them absolute trying to understand how this you
know
changing the mind of a צדוקי, Tzeduki, so he's calling okay, they
make him טמא, tamei they see that. They make him go into
the מקוה, mikvah so this vessel does they actually they treat it
as טמא.
tamei I know, this is bizarre, exactly. Well because the צדוקים Tzadokim.
would say, we don't buy into your absurd idea of having made
this an אב הטומאה, av hatumah. so to us it doesn't look
like a leniency that you're using it right away, right? It's like,
with your own סברא Svara you're being lenient, but that doesn't do
anything for me, right? I don't know the answer to that. The
only thing is that look, if they see since reality is that
it's not just hypothetical, every time they're making these vessels the people
that handle them are have to go to the מקוה. mikvah The
people that handle the vessels before they immersed it become טמא tamei
and go to the מקוה. mikvah, So it's an actual like practice
on the ground, the weight of טומאה tumah that we're treating this
with. So even if they don't sort of believe in it in
theory, they sort of do see in practice that every time these
vessels are made... we're being treated as טמא tamei and people are
going to the מקוה when they handle them before they immerse them.
And nevertheless, you're going to use the vessel right after it went
to the מקוה? So maybe it's some experiential level it still had
that power, but you're right at a theoretical level it's like they
don't buy into the whole created טומאה tumah to think that this
means anything. You're absolutely correct. Okay, yes.
Conceptually, the human body is a paradigm for all of this concept
of a vessel, right? It's a container. Life goes in it and
there's a certain way to understand anthropology.
By
that's alright, that's a good point.
Yeah, so and בגד beged also, in other words, you pick up
the sides of it, as it were, and it's also becomes a
container as it were. I'm just trying to make...
You're trying to make some translation here. Yeah. Okay, it's a very
good point. Alright.
What, yeah, so it becomes- does he buy into that
they're making the כהן kohen טמא tamei, just before he does the
service?
No, but what Michael's saying is if you actually took let's say
a שרץ shereitz and you threw it on the כהן, kohen, they
would all admit that he was טמא. tamei Right. Whereas they wouldn't
admit that this vessel is טמא tamei.
because they don't buy into this.
That, right. Right. Right. The question is here. Right. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. והתניא, Vehatanya, so now the גמרא Gemara
is going to be bothered that we have created this new idea
of turning something into a day seven כלי. kli. והתניא, Vehatanya, did
we not teach in a ברייתא, Baraita, מעולם לא חיסר דבר בפרה.
meolam lo chiser davar beparah. They never like completely invented something new,
meaning they might have created new procedures like saying we're going to
get a טמא tamei. and then we're going to go to the
מקוה whatever, but they didn't like create new categories. You know, they
sort of insisted on doing certain things but they were using existing
categories. They didn't create new categories by פרה אדומה para aduma, and
here you're creating a category of a vessel that was just created
that becomes a day seven vessel. It's a little bizarre. אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, no. Here's what it means. That at least exists as
a category, there is such a thing as a day seven vessel.
Okay, as it- it normally doesn't apply to vessels that were created
an hour ago but that does exist as a halakhic category. But
here's what it means that we didn't create a new category: שלא
אמרו קורדום מטמא מושב. shelo amru kordom metamei moshav. They never said
a hammer is מטמא metamei the טומאה tumah of seat. Like again,
if a זב zav or זבה zavah or נדה niddah sits on
something it becomes an אב הטומאה. av hatuma That's מדרס. midras. That's
מושב, moshav, a seat. So they never said we'll take something that
could not be a מושב moshav like a hammer and say, oh,
this is going to have טומאת מושב. tumat moshav. Which is sort
of what I said. Why didn't they just say that they made
this tube into a מושב, moshav, right? Cause that's a little bit
more simple than say they made it into something that touched a
dead body and had ashes sprinkled on it. Just say they made
it a מושב moshav and it was day seven. אביי Abaye says
no, that they're not going to do. They're not going to say
a tube is a seat. Okay, that it would be a really
completely new category. דתניא Detanya like we taught in the ברייתא. ויושב
על הכלי, Vyoshev al hakli, whoever sits on the
vessel that
a
זב zav sat on... יכול כפה סאה וישב עליה, yachol kaffat seah
veyashav aleha, תרקב וישב עליה, tarkav veyashav aleha, another type of measuring
vessel, יהא טמא, yehei tamei, maybe that would be considered a מושב
moshav of a זב... zav... תלמוד לומר
והיושב על הכלי אשר ישב עליו יטמא. talmud lomar vehayoshev al hakli
asher yeshev alav yitma. The one who sits on a vessel not
that a זב zav sat on, not אשר ישב עליו הזב, asher
yashav alav hazav, but אשר ישב, asher yeshev, that a זב zav
will sit on. So something that is usually sat on, not just
happen to have been sat on. מי שמיוחד לישיבה, mi shemeyuchad liyeshivah,
a vessel that is made for sitting can become a מושב moshav
of a זב. zav. יצא זה שאומרים לו עמוד ונעשה מלאכתנו. yatza
zeh sheomrim lo emod venasseh melachtenu. Suppose there's something like this where
they say what the heck are you doing sitting on our bushel?
Get off of that, we gotta use this, we gotta measure out
the wheat. You have no right to sit on it. So that
means that the only thing that could become a מושב, moshav, not
any vessel can become a מושב moshav just cause a זב zav
happened to sit on it. It has to be something that is
made for sitting. So when we say we did not make new
categories by פרה אדומה, para aduma it's mean we never took something
that could not be a seat and say it has the טומאה
Tumah. of seats. That like is something that can never exist in
הלכה. halakha. What we could say is a vessel that was created
yesterday is like a seven stage vessel because at least the category
we're putting it in fits. And it makes sense that it's something-
it doesn't make sense that it's an
hour- it was only created
yesterday, but at least it fits into that category and therefore we're
able to do it. So the upshot is is that any new
vessel that's made you immerse and use immediately by פרה אדומה, para
aduma is that immersing and using it immediately enough of a way
to undermine the position of the צדוקים? So we have the idea
of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that says no, if you really want
to undermine the צדוקים you gotta get it really טמא, tamei not
just work... within this מעלות, and then immerse it and use it
immediately. רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua says it's enough to immerse and use
it immediately even without getting it טמא. Tamei, Why?
Because we've create, we've made it so טמא tamei, before you immersed
it. We made it as if it was an אב הטומאה av
ha-tumah, and maybe even if the צדוקים don't buy into that, like
Michael said, in practice, if we say that anybody who handles this
has to go to the מקוה and we've made it really טמא
tamei and then we're going to use it right after immersing it,
that'll be enough for us to make our point against the צדוקים.
Okay, so that is the end of the discussion around כלי מאפסל.
kli me-efsal. And now we get to the next מעלה. ma'ala. So
let's take a look.
הכלי מצרף מה שבתוכו לקודש אבל לא לתרומה. Hakli mitsaref ma shebetokho
lekodesh aval lo leteruma. A vessel combines everything inside of it for
קודש kodesh purposes but not for תרומה teruma purposes. What does this
mean? Again, you have a bowl filled with apples. Something טמא tamei
touches one apple. Are the other apples טמא tamei. or not? So
do you say, well apple number one is, I don't know, let's
say an אב touch it. Apple number one is a ראשון. rishon
The apples that it's touching is a שני sheni. and then it
stops there. Or if it's a תרומה teruma bowl, then the apples
that they touch become a שלישי Shelishi. but then it stops there,
right? And it doesn't, you know, it would only be X degrees
of touching what touched what touched, right? Whereas if you say that
it's all one big unit of apples, then whatever touches it makes
everything טמא, tamei makes them all טמא tamei equally. Okay, so for
קודש kodesh, purposes we treat them as all one big unit. For
תרומה teruma purposes we treat them as separate units. Okay, so let's
take a look. מנא הני מילי? Minani milei? Where do you get
this from? So אמר רב חנין, amar Rav Hanin, דאמר קרא, damar
kra, the verse says: כף אחת עשרה זהב מלאה קטורת, Kaf achat
asara zahav mele'a ketoret, by the gift that the נשיאים nesi'im gave,
one ladle, one spoon
worth ten talents of silver—or ten units of silver—filled with incense. הכתוב
עשאו לכלי לכל מה שבכף אחת. Hakasuv asa'o lekli lekhol mah shebakaf
achat. כף אחת. Kaf achat. And it was מלאה קטורת. mele'a ketoret.
So every, it was filled with incense, and incense are tiny little,
you know, bead like, you know, think of like, I don't know,
think of like salt or something like that, you know, tiny little
unit, objects, crystals or whatever they are. And nevertheless it says אחת,
achat, one. So it's like although the אחת achat is going on
the ladle, not on what's in the ladle, it's homiletically reading this
as if everything in the ladle is one unit. And that's קודש,
kodesh so you see for קודש kodesh, purposes it all gets defined
as one unit. So by the way, that seems to make it
a biblical idea. We've been assuming that these are all דרבנן. de-rabbanan.
So there's one—תוספות Tosafos discusses this and so on—it could be—I mean
the גמרא Gemara's is about to discuss it and we'll see—but it
is possible that some of the things on this list are דאורייתא
de-oraita or aspects of them are דאורייתא. de-oraita.
Yes. I'm just going to ask—so you have a basket of apples
and it's clear which apple is which. Right. But you have a
basket of wheat grains that you're going to grind into flour, power—you
can actually identify an individual grain that you touched.
Yeah. It's not about ביטול, bitul, it doesn't matter that you can
identify. It's we consider it one unit and when we say what
did you touch, I don't say well I touched that grain or
I touched the apple. I touched the bushel of apples. I touched
the pile of grain. We think of it—so it's not about the
thing you touched mixed up and ביטול, bitul, it's not about that
at all. It's that you look at the thing that was touched
as not the single unit, the apple or the grain or the
crystal of קטורת, ketoret, but you touched the pile. And as therefore
you touched the pile, you were מטמא metamei the whole pile. Okay,
that's the concept.
Okay. So, okay, so מתיב רב כהנא. mative Rav Kahana. So רב
כהנא Rav Kahana asked on this. הוסיף רבי עקיבא. Hosif Rebbi Akiva.
We have a משנה Mishna עדיות. Edyos. It says רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva added to the list of things that, that when you touch
one, it all becomes טמא. tamei? הסולת, Hasolet, the flour that's being
brought for קודש, kodesh. for like, you know, קדשים kodshim purposes, like
for a מנחה. mincha. הקטורת, Haketoret, the incense, meaning the חידוש. chiddush.
והלבונה, ve-halvona, and frankincense, different type of incense. והגחלים, vehagechalim, and even
the, you know, the coals that are used that you, you shovel
out from the altar in order to burn incense on
them on the מזבח הזהב mizbe'ach hazahav or in the קודש הקדשים
Kodesh Hakodashim on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. בכל אלו, Be'khol elu, in
all those cases, שנגע טבול יום במקצתו פסל את כולו, shenaga tevul
yom bemiktzaso pasal es kulo, that if a טבול יום tevul yom
touch part of it, he makes it all invalid. He's מטמא metamei
it all. פסל. Pasal. A טבול יום tevul yom is somebody who
has a status, gone to the מקוה, has until nightfall, has a
status of a שני. sheni. So,
okay, so what's the big—first of all, part of the חידוש chiddush
we should note about רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva is that these things
aren't food, except maybe סולת, solet, but even that's not edible in
the current state. Okay, and that he's willing to sort of talk
about טומאה Tumah. about non-food objects, which is a whole discussion by
קדשים kodshim that even non-food objects can become טמא. tamei Non-food objects
and non-vessels. But anyway, but part of the חידוש chiddush also is
that it's all treated as one unit. Our idea. Now what does
the גמרא Gemara's say, what's the problem? So the גמרא Gemara's says:
והא דרבנן היא. Veha derabbanan hi. And that thing that רבי עקיבא
Rebbi Akiva is saying clearly is all rabbinic.
ממאי? Mimai? How do you know it's rabbinic? מדתני רישא Mid'katni reisha
because the line that רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva is commenting on that
preceded it says the following: העיד רבי שמעון בן בתירה על אפר
חטאת. He'id Rebbi Shimon ben Betera al efer chatas. רבי שמעון בן
בתירה Rebbi Shimon ben Betera testified on the ashes of the פרה
para, אדומה that you have collected in a vessel שנגע הטמא במקצתו...
shenaga hatamei bemiktzaso... that if a טמא person touched part of it,
he's מטמא metamei all of it. Okay, so he testified on that
and then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva added all these things. מדקתני Mi'dik'tani
and then we said הוסיף רבי עקיבא, Hosif Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva added. Now, what does that, how does that prove that
this is דרבנן? de'rabbanan? Where do you see that this is דרבנן
de'rabbanan as opposed to being דאורייתא? de'oraisa? What does the גמרא Gemara's
say? Right, the whole argument is, oh look, it's all דרבנן de'rabbanan
and you claim from a פסוק passuk כף אחת kaf achas it's
דאורייתא, de'oraisa, here we see it's דרבנן. de'rabbanan. Where do you see
it's דרבנן? de'rabbanan? So רש"י Rashi says we see it's דרבנן de'rabbanan
because it's starting with the line of the ashes of the פרה
אדומה. And the ashes of the פרה אדומה, this might seem ironic,
are not קודש. kodesh. Right? You sanctify the פרה, but the ashes
after you burn it no longer are considered to be קודש. kodesh,
I mean they, they purify but they have no longer any קדושה,
kedusha, they've transformed. So if we are saying that if you touch
part you're מטמא metamei all applies even by the ashes of the
פרה אדומה, we're not limiting our idea to קודש, kodesh right? And
the פסוק passuk כף אחת kaf achas by the קטורת ketores is
by קדשים kodashim and so on. So you see that this is
not really based on the biblical verse, you see that this is
דרבנן de'rabbanan and therefore can apply to even other cases. And then
when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva adds his list, so that list that
he's adding similarly is not דאורייתא. de'oraisa. The same way the first
statement is דרבנן, de'rabbanan, the things that he's adding are also דרבנן.
de'rabbanan. Okay? That's how רש"י Rashi sort of frames how the גמרא's
Gemara proving it's דרבנן de'rabbanan because the case we start with is
ashes of a פרה אדומה which in no way could be based
on the verse about the incense because ashes of the פרה אדומה
have no קודש kodesh status at all.
That's not true that דשן על גבי המזבח, deshen al gabei ha'mizbei'ach,
but the other ashes.
Right, so other stuff. Well, no, that's, so תוספות Tosafos has a
whole, one of the big תוספות Tosafos is discussing that about when
you shovel out the coals, do they become קודש kodesh. or not?
If they spilled do you have to, how do you dispose of
them and so on? So it's complicated, okay? And certainly some of
the things in רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's list are definitely קודש. kodesh,
סולת, Soles, קטורת, ketores, לבונה. levona. But anyway, but since the first
thing is not קודש, kodesh, the גמרא's Gemara saying that רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva it's not דאורייתא de'oraisa because it's not קודש, kodesh. the
גמרא's Gemara saying the rest of the things on רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva's list are also not דאורייתא. de'oraisa. It's funny why it brings
a proof from רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, doesn't bring a proof from
the, from the original statement. Anyway, the גמרא's Gemara. understanding is that
this is דרבנן. de'rabbanan. So how could you quote a פסוק passuk
and say it's דאורייתא? de'oraisa? So let's see what the גמרא says.
אמר ריש לקיש משום בר קפרא, Amar Reish Lakish mishum Bar Kappara,
so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says in the name of בר קפרא,
Bar Kappara, דף פ"ב עמוד א', Daf Pey Beis amud Aleph, לא
נצרכה אלא לשירי מנחה. Lo nitzrecha ela le'shirei mincha. It's only,
the חידוש, chiddush, the דרבנן de'rabbanan aspect is for the leftover stuff.
What does that mean? The leftover מנחה. mincha. After you brought the
קומץ komets of the מנחה, mincha, what's left over of the מנחה
mincha is eaten by the כהנים kohanim and then when it's left
over and it's in a vessel somebody touches it, there it's you
know, touches part is מטמא metamei all, there it's only דרבנן. de'rabbanan.
Why is it different? It's still קודש. kodesh. What makes that only
דרבנן? de'rabbanan? So it says דאורייתא, De'oraisa, because דאורייתא de'oraisa we would
say the following: צריך לכלי הכלי מצרפו. Tzarich likli hakli mitzarfo. Something
that needs the vessel, the vessel unites them. Meaning, why would something
need a vessel? It's not just need a vessel because you need
to stop your apples from rolling off of the table, that doesn't
count as needing a vessel. Needing a vessel means הלכתית halachically the
vessel is needed to give it its status. So what the גמרא
is saying is like this: this only applies by קודש. kodesh, Remember
we said it only applies by קודש, kodesh right? And that even
applies דאורייתא, de'oraisa, but under the following circumstances: when you put it
in a כלי שרת kli shareis and you need the כלי kli
to impart the sanctity, that's when the כלי kli unifies everything in
it. But as soon as you no longer need the כלי kli
to impart the sanctity, then the כלי kli does not unify. So
when do you no longer need the כלי kli to impart the
sanctity? Well, after it is now has been offered up and now
you're just left with the remainder and actually what you could do
is you could take it out of a כלי שרת. kli shareis.
You could go ahead and put it on your plate and eat
it. Until you offered it, you needed it in the כלי שרת.
kli shareis. Since you needed it in the כלי, kli, the כלי
kli unified it. But after you've, after you've offered the קומץ komets
and you're going to eat the rest, you can put it on
your paper plate. So it no longer needs a vessel and since
it doesn't need הלכתית halachically a vessel, there's no longer a sense
of unifying. By the way, תוספות Tosafos said there, if that's true,
there was a much easier answer. The גמרא could have just said
we're talking about, you know when you need the דרבנן? de'rabbanan? When
it's not in a כלי שרת. kli shareis. You have your קודש
kodesh not in a כלי שרת. kli shareis. Because what we're now
saying is the only time biblically the idea that the vessel unifies
is when it's in a כלי שרת kli shareis and it has
to be in a כלי שרת. kli shareis. That's the only time
that the, that it's unified because then it needs to be in
that vessel and הלכתית halachically and that's what unifies it. But if
it's not in a כלי שרת kli shareis or doesn't have to
be, then it's, then it's only a rabbinic standard. Okay? So דאורייתא
צריך לכלי הכלי מצרפו, De'oraisa tzarich likli hakli mitzarfo, if it needs
to be in that vessel, in that כלי שרת, kli shareis, then
the כלי שרת kli shareis unifies it.
שאין צריך לכלי אין כלי מצרפו, She'ein tzarich likli ein kli mitzarfo,
it does not unify it.
ואתו רבנן וגזרו, Ve'asu rabbanan ve'gazru, and the rabbis came and they
decreed דאף על גב דאינו צריך לכלי, de'af al gav de'aino tzarich
likli, even when it no longer needs to be in the vessel,
even if it's you know, if, if you can now ahead transfer
it to a paper plate and it doesn't have to be
in a כלי שרת, kli shareis, nevertheless כלי מצרפו. kli mitzarfo. So
that's where you need the דרבנן de-rabanan when it's not in the
כלי שרת kli shareis or it no longer has to be in
it, in it, or it's in it but doesn't have to be
in it. Gemara says one minute, תינח סולת, teinach soles, that's good
for the case of the flour, that there's a point where it
no longer has to be in the vessel, because you already offered
up the handbreadth, the קומץ. kometz. But קטורת ולבונה ktoris u-levona מה
איכא למימר? mai ika le-meimar? How about the incense and the two
types of the incense, one that you use for the לחם הפנים,
lechem ha-panim, the other that you burn on the מזבח הזהב, mizbeach
ha-zahav, right? Those always have to be in the כלי שרת kli
shareis and then after they and then they go straight onto the
altar, right, straight onto the מזבח הזהב. mizbeach ha-zahav. So when do
you ever have a case that those don't have to be in
a כלי שרת? kli shareis? So Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha, כגון שצבירן
על גבי קרטבלא. kegon she-tziviran al gabei kartavla. Okay, so here's the
scenario: that actually you put them, you know, on a, on a,
like רש״י says like on a, like a platform, like it was
a flat vessel. דאורייתא, de-oraisa, because biblically, יש לו תוך מצרף, yesh
lo toch mtzaref, אין לו תוך אינו מצרף. ein lo toch einu
mtzaref.
Biblically, the idea of unifying it would come only if it's a
vessel that has an inside, that actually has like a cavity, because
if it doesn't have a cavity, if it's a flat vessel, then
it doesn't unify. ואתו רבנן ותיקנו דאף על גב דאין לו תוך
מצרף ve-atu rabanan ve-tiknu de-af al gav de-ein lo toch mtzarfo and
the rabbis come along and said even without an inside it still
unifies. So basically is this idea that the vessel unifies and makes
it one unit for טומאה Tumah. purposes for קודש kodesh דאורייתא de-oraisa
or דרבנן? de-rabanan? So we're saying it's דאורייתא de-oraisa in the following
circumstances: when it's a כלי שרת, kli shareis, when it needs to
be in a כלי שרת, kli shareis, and when it has a
cavity. But if you're missing any of those criteria, then it's not
דאורייתא de-oraisa but it is דרבנן. de-rabanan. So in one way certain
aspects of this are rabbinic, aspects are דאורייתא, de-oraisa, but by קודש
kodesh the vessel unifies everything. Okay. ופליגא דרבי חנינא u-pliga de-Rabbi Chanina
and that statement of רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina that says that there's
a דאורייתא de-oraisa component and a דרבנן de-rabanan component argues on רבי
חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba. דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, מעדותו
של רבי עקיבא נשנית משנה זו, me-eduso shel Rabbi Akiva nishnis mishna
zu, that our משנה mishna that speaks about the vessel unifying is
following the position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that we quoted that
says the vessel unifies all these objects. So why is that against
him? Because we have said that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is דרבנן.
de-rabanan. So this last statement is saying that our משנה, mishna, if
it's going like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, is saying that the דין
din in our משנה mishna is all a rabbinic דין. din. And
that's against what we have said. We've said there are times that
that will be a biblical דין din when it's a כלי שרת
kli shareis and it needs to be in the vessel. Okay, so
is that clear? We have רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's statement
that says the vessel unifies. Gemara has decided for a somewhat unclear
reason that that's a rabbinic statement. Okay. We've also said that the
הלכה halacha that the כלי kli unifies in our משנה mishna is
biblical. So how do we deal with that? We'll say well there
are two things: there's a biblical aspect and a rabbinic aspect. Biblical
when it's a כלי שרת, kli shareis, it needs to be in
the כלי, kli, it has a cavity. Rabbinic other times. And now
we say but by the way there's another opinion out there that
our משנה mishna is all rabbinic and it goes like רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and there's no biblical idea here at all and the
whole הלכה halacha is completely rabbinic. Okay, so that's the question: is
the whole הלכה halacha rabbinic or is there a biblical part and
a rabbinic part? Let's get let's now do another at least another
one. Okay, now, הרביעי בקודש פסול. ha-revii ba-kodesh pasul. So
onto next מעלה. ma'ala. And this is by the way I would
say the most like you know just general הלכה halacha about a
difference between קודש kodesh and תרומה teruma is that קודש Kodesh goes
up to four levels of derivation and תרומה teruma only goes up
to three levels of derivation. Okay? So people got it again? You
got your אב הטומאה, you got your carcass of an animal or
your זב zav or whatever, he touches a person, the person is
a ראשון. Rishon, Person's now no now you take all people and
vessels out of the equation because only people and vessels can only
be ראשון and no further. Okay. The only thing from after ראשון
on is food. Okay, actually why don't we even make a chart?
Okay, let's
go.
What happened to my
do I not have my thing?
Well I have a I have a thing.
Everybody close your eyes. It's in a very hard place to open.
Okay, I know.
Okay,
so, here's your, here's your dead animal.
It's very insensitive by the way.
You like the X's on the eyes? Here's your dead animal. That's
your אב, okay? He touches a person or a I don't know
a vessel, okay? That's a ראשון. Okay. Only people and vessels can
be a ראשון. They stop after that. From this point on it's
just going to be food. How are we going to demonstrate food?
An apple, thank you. Okay. From this point on, so from this
point on it's only food. Okay.
People you know people
and vessels are only at the ראשון status. Okay. That's going to
be now that can be חולין, chullin, that's a שני. Sheni, Okay.
After this, the next apple, it all goes back to that apple,
right, from Adam and Eve. Anyway. And then after that, it's all
going to be food, okay? But what you need to be able
to go down to the next stage is higher degrees of טומאה.
Tumah, Okay, so here you are חולין Chullin can become a שני,
Sheni. here תרומה Terumah can become a שלישי, Shelishi, and קודש Kodesh
can become a רביעי Revi'i and then it stops.
And the last word דרבנן? DeRabbanan?
Well, we're going to see, okay? It might actually be דאורייתא, De'Oraita,
it's a question. Okay, so let's take a look now. So the
big difference is תרומה Terumah can be a שלישי, Shelishi. קודש Kodesh
can be a רביעי. Revi'i.
Wait, so the דאורייתא, De'Oraita, the dead animal's not the only
source as an אב?
No, it's not, but I didn't, it wasn't as easy to draw
a זב Zav or a זבה Zavah or a נידה. Niddah. Okay,
and I didn't want to draw a dead person because that's an
אבי אבות. Avi Avot. Okay? If you want to start with a
dead person, a מת, okay, you could have the מת which is
an אבי אבות, Avi Avot, right, the granddaddy, and then a person
touches a dead body and if a person
here touched the dead body, so then he would be an אב.
Okay. And the other types of אב you have are, you know,
זב, Zav, זבה, Zavah, נידה, Niddah, משכב Mishkav of a
זב Zav and
a
זבה Zavah and a נידה, Niddah, okay, שרץ.
Okay?
Okay, so that's a lot, right.
Okay, most of the big categories in the תורה Torah in תזריע,
Tazria, מצורע, Metzora, or whatever, you know, are or and elsewhere are
the אב אבות, Av Avot, right? Okay, those are the sources of
טומאה. Tumah All right? Okay, so let's take a look. רביעי בקודש
פסול. Revi'i BeKodesh Pasul. תניא, it says in
a ברייתא, אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, מניין לרביעי בקודש שהוא
פסול? Minayin LeRevi'i BeKodesh SheHu Pasul? How do you know? So again,
we've already introduced the idea that some of these might be דאורייתא
De'Oraita and here it seems that this might be דאורייתא De'Oraita as
well. How do you know the idea that the fourth derivation in
קודש kodesh is פסול? Pasul? ודין הוא, VeDin Hu, it makes sense.
ומה מחוסר כיפורים שמותר בתרומה פסול בקודש. Umah Mechussar Kippurim SheMuttar BeTerumah
Pasul BeKodesh. מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim is a person that has been
טמא, let's say it's one of those extended טומאות, Tumot, let's say
a זב, Zav, זבה, Zavah, נידה, Niddah, been to the מקווה, Mikveh,
brought a... you have to bring a קרבן Korban to end the
זב Zav and the זבה Zavah period. Brought a קרבן Korban the
next... wait, is waiting now in the morning to bring the קרבן.
Korban.
Okay? So waiting to bring the קרבן Korban is considered מחוסר כיפורים,
Mechussar Kippurim, lacking bringing his final
cleansing קרבן. Korban. And therefore he still has residual טומאה. Tumah, Okay?
So he basically has a status similar to being a שלישי. Shelishi
Okay? A person that is...
a person that is הערב שמש, Ha'erev Shemesh, okay? הערב שמש Ha'erev
Shemesh means,
here you are, you've gone to the מקווה. Mikveh. Okay, I don't
know, we'll draw how we're going to draw a מקווה Mikveh here?
I don't know. A מקווה Mikveh with water, here you are, you're
still dripping wet, you've gone to the מקווה. Mikveh. It... okay, so
you have... so you have actually no, this is... I'm sorry. טבול
יום. Tevul Yom. טבול יום Tevul Yom is you've gone and it's
still daytime. So you are effectively, effectively, not really but effectively a
שני. Sheni Okay? Then you have that it's sunset. Okay, here, the
sun went below the horizon. Okay? Then it becomes הערב שמש. Ha'erev
Shemesh. Okay? Now, you would then be טהור Tahor, unless you needed
to bring a קרבן. Korban. If you needed to now bring a
קרבן, Korban, here you are and here's your קרבן, Korban, so you're
likely bringing a קרבן Korban because you're a זב Zav or a
זבה Zavah or a מצורע Metzora and you haven't brought your קרבן
Korban yet. So before you've brought your קרבן, Korban, okay, you are
considered מחוסר כיפורים. Mechussar Kippurim. Okay? So some people in here, but
if you're a זב Zav and a זבה Zavah and a מצורע
Metzora and you still have to bring your קרבן Korban the next
day. Okay, I don't know how we're going to demonstrate, I'll draw
a whole בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, here's your מזבח Mizbe'ach and whatever,
anyway fine. Okay, your מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim and then you are
effectively a שלישי. Shelishi So if you don't have to bring a
קרבן Korban after nightfall, okay, then you become טהור. Tahor If you
have to bring a קרבן, Korban, then before you bring your קרבן
Korban you're still a שלישי, Shelishi, that's the status of מחוסר כיפורים.
Mechussar Kippurim. Okay? I don't know, that's not as well visually done
as that but you get the idea. So let's take a look.
Okay.
So חולין Chullin isn't the only thing that can be a שלישי.
shlishi, Well, right, although this is effectively, this is not a third
derivation טומאה, Tumah. this is residual טומאה tumah that has not completely
been
purified from. You understand? So these are like derivations, how many degrees
removed. Here you are cleansing yourself from your טומאה, you're an
אב or ראשון,
okay,
but there's a little left. There's something residual and that effectively you'll
be a שני Sheni, until it's nightfall. Okay, until it's just move
that until it's nightfall you'll be a שני, Sheni then after at
night you become טהור, and if you need to bring a קרבן,
Korban, so if you need to bring a קרבן, Korban, you know,
it's either you're טהור or you're a שלישי shlishi, if you need
to bring a קרבן. Korban.
And that's very clarifying. So basically what we're saying conceptually is you
have two different types of שני Sheni and שלישי shlishi of טומאה.
Right, although they never call this a שני sheni and שלישי, shlishi
they say a טבול יום Tevul Yom can't eat תרומה, Terumah, a
מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim can eat תרומה. Terumah. Which is exactly what
would happen with a שני sheni and שלישי, shlishi, but they don't
use those terms because it's not—it's the same הלכה, halakha, but the
etiology's different. Exactly. And right, and a שני שלישי sheni shlishi means
degrees of derivation. This is not derived, you know, it's residual. So
let's read that. Okay, so מנלן לרביעי בקודש שהוא פסול? Menalan l'revi'i
bakodesh shehu pasul? ודין הוא. V'din hu. It makes sense that a
רביעי revi'i would not be able
to—that קודש kodesh could become a רביעי. revi'i. ומה מחוסר כיפורים—and Umah
mechusar kippurim the guy who's waiting to bring his קרבן, korban, which
we now have said is effectively a שלישי, shlishi. can't eat קרבנות
korbanot yet,
שמותר בתרומה—can shemutar biterumah eat תרומה, terumah, פסול בקודש—will pasul bakodesh invalidate
קרבנות, korbanot, so שלישי שפסול בתרומה, shlishi shepasul biterumah, something that is
food that is a
שלישי shlishi that is invalid תרומה—of terumah תרומה terumah becomes invalid if
it's a שלישי—אינו דין שיעשה רביעי revi'i. לקודש? How much more so
should it go ahead and be able to make קודש into a
רביעי. revi'i. Now, to make it simplified, here's basically the concept. This
guy who's the מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar kippurim, he can't eat קדשים, kadshim,
right? He but he can eat תרומה. terumah. So somebody who can
handle תרומה, terumah, who won't be מטמא metamei תרומה, terumah, what would
that person have to be? The only thing that won't be מטמא
תרומה terumah is a שלישי, shlishi right? Because a שני sheni. will
make תרומה terumah into a שלישי. shlishi, So this that's why this
person is effectively a שלישי shlishi because we know he's allowed to
handle תרומה. terumah. Well, he's allowed to handle תרומה, terumah, but he
can't handle קרבנות, korbanot, he can't eat קרבנות. korbanot. That means that
קרבנות korbanot must be able to become a רביעי. revi'i. Okay? So
the fact that this guy can handle תרומה terumah and not קרבנות
korbanot shows you that there's one level lower that קרבנות korbanot can
go to be טמא, that even with a residual טומאה that won't
affect תרומה, terumah, it will affect the קרבן. korban. So therefore, if
something is a שלישי shlishi, and you really have תרומה טמאה terumah
tmeiah that's a שלישי, shlishi. then it should have the ability to
take the קרבן korban one level further into a רביעי. revi'i Let's
just finish the גמרא. Okay. ולמדנו שלישי לקודש מן התורה ורביעי מקל
וחומר. V'lamadnu shlishi lakodesh min haTorah v'revi'i mikal vachomer.
Now we know that קרבנות korbanot can become a שלישי shlishi from
the תורה, Torah, and now we've learned that they become a רביעי
revi'i from the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What's the תורה? Torah? שלישי
לקודש מן התורה מנלן? Shlishi lakodesh min haTorah menalan? דכתיב והבשר אשר
יגע בכל טמא לא
יאכל—that Dechtiv vehabasar asher yiga bechol tamei lo ye'achel meat of a
sacrifice that touches anything טמא cannot be eaten. Now, anything טמא means
anything the תורה Torah has declared טמא. Now if you look through
the cases in the תורה, Torah, one of the scenarios that the
תורה Torah talks about something becoming טמא is it becoming a שני.
sheni, רש"י Rashi discusses it, okay? Where a שרץ touches something and
touches food and whatever. So, and here it says anything טמא will
make a קרבן, korban, will be a problem for a קרבן. korban.
So מי לא עסקינן—are mi lo askinan we not talking about דנגע
בשני—that denaga b'sheni it even touched a שני, because that's a clear
case in
the תורה Torah of something
טמא? ואמר רחמנא לא יאכל. V'amar rachmana lo ye'achel. So you see
that a קרבן korban can become a שלישי, because it says anything
טמא a קרבן korban touches is a problem. So a קרבן korban
can become a שלישי. רביעי מקל וחומר—and Revi'i mikal vachomer the רביעי
revi'i. is the קל וחומר kal vachomer הדא דאמרן—what hada d'amran we
just said—that if this person can eat a תרומה, terumah, can't eat
a קרבן, korban, so something that's really תרומה טמאה terumah tmeiah like
that's a שלישי certainly would make a קרבן korban into a problem
into a רביעי. Okay, we will end here.
Yes.